<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mausoleum or, The choisest flowres of the epitaphs, written on the death of the neuer-too-much lamented Prince Henrie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839727</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839727</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4175</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1241:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mausoleum or, The choisest flowres of the epitaphs, written on the death of the neuer-too-much lamented Prince Henrie</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andro Hart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Poems in English, Italian, and Latin.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4175:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4175:1"/>
            <p>MAVSOLEVM OR, <hi>THE CHOISEST FLOWRES</hi> of the Epitaphs, written on the Death <hi>of the neuer-too-much lamented</hi> PRINCE HENRIE.</p>
            <q>Coſa bella mortal paſſa, e non dura.</q>
            <p>EDINBVRGH Printed by <hi>Andro Hart.</hi> ANNO DOM. 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:4175:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4175:2"/>
            <head>MAVSOLEVM<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>OR,</hi> THE CHOISEST FLOWRES OF <hi>the Epitaphs, written on the Death of the neuer</hi>-too-much lamented PRINCE HENRY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="epitaph">
               <head>EPIT. 1</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oe here intomb'd a peereleſſe Prince doth lie,</l>
                  <l>In flowre and ſtrength of age ſurpryſ'd by Death,</l>
                  <l>On whom, while he on Earth drew vitall breath,</l>
                  <l>The hope of many Kingdomes did relie;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not without cauſe: for Heauens moſt liberally</l>
                  <l>To him all Princely Vertues did bequeath,</l>
                  <l>Which to the worthieſt Princes here beneath</l>
                  <l>Before had bene allotted ſeuerally.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when the world of all his Vertues rare</l>
                  <l>The wiſhed fruit to gather did expect,</l>
                  <l>And that he ſhould ſuch <hi>glorious workes</hi> effect,</l>
                  <l>As with the worthieſt Fame might him compare</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Untimely death then from vs did him take,</l>
                  <l>Our loſſe, and griefe, Heauens gaine, and joy to make.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Q.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="epitaph">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>OCcidit ante diem juvenum flos, gloria ſtirpis</l>
               <l>Regalis, Patriae ſpes, columenq ſuae.</l>
               <l>Occidit ante diem patri, populiſque Britannis</l>
               <l>Flendus, &amp; his junctis foedere, amore, ſacris.</l>
               <l>Occidit ante diem, geſturus Principe digna,</l>
               <l>Acceleraſſet et ni fera Parca necem.</l>
               <l>Occidit ante diem, virtutis &amp; ubere fructu,</l>
               <l>Et mundum exemplo funere destituens.</l>
               <l>Occidit ante diem, ſi vota &amp; commoda ſpectes</l>
               <l>Publica, vel vitam ſi brevitate notes.</l>
               <l>Sin vitam ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes partam illi morte perennem,</l>
               <l>Haud jam, par Superis, occidit ante diem</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Walter Quin.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:4175:3"/>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>STay Paſſenger, ſee where encloſed lyes,</l>
               <l>The Paragon of Princes, faireſt Frame,</l>
               <l>Time, Nature, Place could ſhow to mortall eyes,</l>
               <l>In Worth, Wit, Vertue; wonder vnto Fame.</l>
               <l>At leaſt that part the Earth of him could claime,</l>
               <l>This Marble holds <hi>hard like the Deſtinies:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as to his braue Spirit, and glorious Name,</l>
               <l>The one the World, the other fills the Skyes.</l>
               <l>Th'immortall <hi>Amaranthus,</hi> princelie <hi>Roſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Violet,</hi> and that ſweet flowre that beares</l>
               <l>In ſanguine ſpots the tenor of our woes,</l>
               <l>Spred on this ſtone, and waſh it with thy teares.</l>
               <l>Then goe and tell from <hi>Gades</hi> vnto <hi>Inde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou ſaw where Earths perfections were confinde.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="epitaph">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>A Paſſing glance, a lightning long the ſkies</l>
               <l>That vſh'ring thunder dies ſtraight to our ſight,</l>
               <l>A ſparke, of contraries that doth ariſe</l>
               <l>Then's drown'd in the huge deepes of Day and Night:</l>
               <l>Is this ſmall ſmall cald life, held in ſuch price</l>
               <l>Of blinded Wights, who ne're judge ought aright.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Parthian</hi> ſhaft ſo ſwift is not the flight,</l>
               <l>As lyfe, that waſtes it ſelfe, and liuing dies.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ah,</hi> what is humane Greatneſſe, Valour, Wit?</l>
               <l>What fading Beautie, Riches, Honour, Praiſe?</l>
               <l>To what doth ſerue in golden thrones to ſit,</l>
               <l>Thrall Earths vaſte Round, triumphall Arches raiſe?</l>
               <l>That all's a Dreame learne in this Princes fall,</l>
               <l>In whom ſade Death naught mortall was at all.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:4175:3"/>
               <head>5</head>
               <l>OF JET,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>PORPHERIE,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or that white ſtone</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>PAROS</hi> affoordes alone,</l>
               <l>Or theſe in <hi>AZVRE</hi> dye,</l>
               <l>which ſeeme to ſcorne the <hi>SKYE:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here <hi>Memphis</hi> Wonders doe not ſet,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>ARTEMISIA'S</hi> huge frame,</l>
               <l>that keepes ſo long her Louers Name:</l>
               <l>mak no great marble <hi>Atlas</hi> tremble with gold</l>
               <l>To pleaſe a vulgar eye that doth beholde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus,</hi> the Muſes, Loue, hath raiſed of their teares</l>
               <l>A Chryſtal tombe to him where through his worth appear</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Drummond.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:4175:4"/>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>FAire <hi>Britaines</hi> Prince in th' Aprill of his yeares,</l>
               <l>The Heauen [enamour'd with his ſpringing grace]</l>
               <l>Reſt to her ſelfe, for to enriche the Spheares,</l>
               <l>And ſhine next <hi>Cynthia</hi> in the ſtarrie chaſe.</l>
               <l>And well enjoy he might ſo high a place;</l>
               <l>For frowning <hi>Neptunes</hi> liquid field of feares,</l>
               <l>And this poore mote of duſt that all vpbeares,</l>
               <l>To his great mind ſeem'd too too ſmall a ſpace:</l>
               <l>Yet it his coarſe doth keepe; [deare pledge] ou'r which</l>
               <l>Affections flammes huge <hi>Pyramides</hi> doth raiſe,</l>
               <l>All grauen with golden letters of his praiſe.</l>
               <l>But <hi>ah</hi> depriued of a gemme ſo riche!</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Britaine</hi> now but great to all appeares,</l>
               <l>In her great loſſe, and <hi>Oceans</hi> of teares.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ignoto.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="epitaph">
               <head>7</head>
               <l>Ciò ch' il Pianéta che diſtíngue L'hore</l>
               <l>Alluma e cínge, e cio ch' il gran Mar laua,</l>
               <l>Tutto quel è la ſepoltura cava,</l>
               <l>Del magnanimo <hi>ARRIGO,</hi> ricco d' Honore.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ignoto.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="epitaph">
               <head>8</head>
               <l>WHy Pilgrime doeſt thou ſtray</l>
               <l>By <hi>Aſia's</hi> floods renown'd?</l>
               <l>Or where great ATLAS crown'd</l>
               <l>With clowds, him reaches boue Heauens milkie way?</l>
               <l>Strange Wonders to behold.</l>
               <l>By <hi>Iſis</hi> ſtreames if thou'l but daigne to ſtay,</l>
               <l>One thou ſhall finde ſurpaſſing all the told.</l>
               <l>For there's in litle roome,</l>
               <l>The PRINCE of men, and <hi>Man</hi> of Princes Tombe.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ignoto.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:4175:4"/>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>HEre lies the Worlds delight,</l>
               <l>Dead to our ſight, but in Eternall light.</l>
               <l>Theſe nyne who by him mone,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> were (alas)</l>
               <l>But through his fatall caſe,</l>
               <l>Are chang'd like wailing <hi>Niobe</hi> in ſtone.</l>
               <l>She clad in Sable roabes,</l>
               <l>Who in a deadly ſleepe</l>
               <l>Such pearlie ſtreames poures from her Chriſtall globes;</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Vertue</hi> that complaines</l>
               <l>She wanteth <hi>Argos</hi> hundreth eyes to weepe;</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Iris</hi> ſiluer raines.</l>
               <l>That wing'd <hi>Penthaſilea</hi> in the Aire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fame</hi> is, his praiſe who roles,</l>
               <l>Twixt both the ſtarrie Poles.</l>
               <l>With earneſt eyes to skies, and Bay-crown'd haire,</l>
               <l>Enſtall'd on <hi>Vertues</hi> throne,</l>
               <l>This Ghaiſtlie Syre that tramples pale <hi>Deſpaire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Braue <hi>Honor's</hi> cald, who ſcornes to giue a grone,</l>
               <l>For in the Programme of his life he reeds,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mens Hopes of him ſurmounts</hi> ALCIDES <hi>deeds.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ignoto.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="epitaph">
               <head>10</head>
               <l>CRudeli crudaque Patri, Patriaeque ruina</l>
               <l>Raptus, ut aethereis inſereretur avis:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>HENRICVS</hi> modicae (Sanctum Caput) inditur Vrna,</l>
               <l>Maximus Ille, ſuo ni genitore minor.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hugo Hollandus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="epitaph">
               <head>11</head>
               <l>DEath (that by ſtealth did wound Prince HENRIES heart)</l>
               <l>Is now tane Captiue, and doth act the part</l>
               <l>Of one o'recome, by being too too fierce,</l>
               <l>And lyes himſelfe dead vnder <hi>Henries</hi> Hearſe:</l>
               <l>He therefore now in Heauenly runes doth ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hell where's thy triumph? Death where is thy ſting?</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>George Wyther.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="epitaph">
               <pb facs="tcp:4175:5"/>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>TWo Kingdomes ſtrove for Intreſt in one Prince,</l>
               <l>Heauens claim'd me from them both, and reſt me hence:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> my Cradle, <hi>England</hi> hath my Herſe,</l>
               <l>The Heauens my Soule, my Vertues liue in Verſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="epitaph">
               <head>13</head>
               <l>I liv'd three Kingdomes hope, foes terror, parents life,</l>
               <l>I di'de their deareſt loſſe, their joy, their endleſſe griefe.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Robert Allyne.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="epitaph">
               <head>14</head>
               <l>WHom all the vaſte frame of the fixed Earth</l>
               <l>Shrunke vnder: now a weake Herſe ſtands beneath:</l>
               <l>His Fate he paſt in fact, in hope his Birth,</l>
               <l>His youth in good life, and in ſpirit his death.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="epitaph">
               <head>15</head>
               <l>BLeſt be his great Begetter, bleſt the Wombe</l>
               <l>That gaue him birth, though much too neere his Tombe.</l>
               <l>In them was he, and they in him were bleſt:</l>
               <l>What their moſt great pow'rs gaue him, was his leaſt.</l>
               <l>His Perſon grac't the Earth, and of the Skyes,</l>
               <l>His bleſſed Spirit, the praiſe is, and the pryſe.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Geor. Chapman.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="epitaph">
               <head>16</head>
               <l>DId he die young? oh no, it could not be,</l>
               <l>For I know few that liv'd ſo long but he,</l>
               <l>Till God and all men lov'd him: then be bold,</l>
               <l>That man that liv's ſo long, muſt needs be old.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>William Rowley.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4175:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
